<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The defence of sundry positions &amp; scriptures for the Congregational-way justified: or An answer to an epistle written by Mr. Richard Hollingworth, unto S.E. and T.T. wherein he (in many particulars) chargeth them with injurious dealing against God, and against himselfe, in that booke of theirs, called A defence of sundry positions, &amp;c. Containing a vindication from such charges and aspersions so laid upon them. As also a briefe answer to his large (if not unreasonable) demands, to have scripturall, or rationall answ. given to his 112 queries. / By Sam: Eaton teacher Tim: Taylor pastor [brace] of [brace] the church at Duckenfield in Cheshire. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E346_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24943</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872076</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E346[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The defence of sundry positions &amp; scriptures for the Congregational-way justified: or An answer to an epistle written by Mr. Richard Hollingworth, unto S.E. and T.T. wherein he (in many particulars) chargeth them with injurious dealing against God, and against himselfe, in that booke of theirs, called A defence of sundry positions, &amp;c. Containing a vindication from such charges and aspersions so laid upon them. As also a briefe answer to his large (if not unreasonable) demands, to have scripturall, or rationall answ. given to his 112 queries. / By Sam: Eaton teacher Tim: Taylor pastor [brace] of [brace] the church at Duckenfield in Cheshire. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Taylor, Timothy, 1611 or 12-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons, for Henry Overton, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 29th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hollingworth, Richard, 1607-1656.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DEFENCE Of ſundry POSITIONS &amp; SCRIPTURES FOR THE Congregational-way JUSTIFIED: OR An Anſwer to an Epiſtle written by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Richard Hollingworth,</hi> unto <hi>S. E.</hi> and <hi>T. T.</hi> wherein he (in many particulars) chargeth them with injurious dealing againſt God, and againſt himſelfe, in that Booke of theirs, called <hi>A Defence of ſundry Poſitions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING A Vindication from ſuch Charges and aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo laid upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo a briefe Anſwer to his large (if not unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi>) demands, to have Scripturall, or rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Anſw. given to his 112. Queries.</p>
            <p>By SAM: EATON Teacher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>IM: TAYLOR Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenfield</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons,</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Popes</hi>-head-Alley. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:159806:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159806:2"/>
            <head>To the Seeker of <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Sincerity,</hi> DIRECTIONS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN BROTHER, <hi>that lookeſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and art willing and deſirous through</hi> Chriſt <hi>to ſearch after and to</hi> receive the love of the Truth, <hi>that thou mayeſt</hi> be ſaved, <hi>and mayeſt further know and</hi> worſhip <hi>our God, and</hi> Father <hi>in Chriſt acceptably,</hi> in ſpirit and in truth, <hi>to glorifie his Name before men,</hi> wherein thou haſt prophaned and polluted it, as we have done, <hi>by</hi> conforming (<hi>with the times</hi>) to the precepts and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raditions of men: <hi>Ponder with us for thy</hi> direction <hi>theſe particulars. 1. That the</hi> Myſtery <hi>of truth is not</hi> manifeſt <hi>to the</hi> World, <hi>the generality, but</hi> to the Saints, <hi>who are dead to the World,</hi> John 14. 22. <hi>&amp; 17. 6. Col. 1. 26. &amp; 2: 20. &amp; 3: 3: 2. Hence this is found amongſt</hi> them <hi>that are moſt</hi> full of love, <hi>Gal. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. John 13. 35. He that</hi> dwells (<hi>or</hi> abides) in that love; abides in God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God in him, 1 John 4. 16. 3. <hi>Hence it's amongſt</hi> them that to others ſo doe, as they would be done unto, Mat. 7. 12. <hi>And that</hi> whatſoever they would not ſhould be done to themſelves, doe not it to others. (Act. 15: 20. 29. <hi>Old Tranſl.</hi> Margin. <hi>v. 20. Regim. v. 29. Complut. Regius</hi> in Naturali &amp; Graec. vetuſt. &amp; optimis, aitinſig. <hi>Selden</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Anno Civile, <hi>c. 21. &amp;</hi> De Jure Gent. <hi>li 7. c. 12.) 4. It's amongſt the pitifull. That</hi> yee ſeeke to the fatherleſſe and widowes in their affliction, and keepe themſelves unſpotted from the world, John 1 27. 5. <hi>This</hi> Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dome <hi>is not from below, but</hi> from above, <hi>and</hi> is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, well-perſwaded, (<hi>or rightly obedient</hi>) full of mercy Jam. 3. 17. 6. <hi>It's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch, as</hi> living godly in Chriſt Jeſus; ſuffer perſecution for his Names fake, 2 Tim. 3. 12. John 15. 19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 16: 33. Mat. 5. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now if thou hardly kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weſt ſuch; Say to</hi> him whom thy ſoul loveth, O tell mee where thou feedeſt, where thou makeſt thy flocks lye down, Cant. 1. 7. <hi>and</hi> he will give <hi>true</hi> wiſedome to thee, <hi>to diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and things that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:159806:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet expect not a</hi> Roſe <hi>without a</hi> pricke <hi>or ſpot. In many things we ſlip all. If any ſlip not in word, he is perfect,</hi> Jam. 3. 2. <hi>Expect therefore to finde this, amongſt them, that in their generall aime and courſe,</hi> walke neareſt according to that Rule, Gal. 6. 16. <hi>And be a</hi> doer of the will of God, <hi>as far as thou knoweſt,</hi> John 7. 17. <hi>and mainly</hi> be taken up <hi>with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Grace, <hi>and love</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, that thy heart may be eſtabliſhed therewith, Heb. 13. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For our parts, ſhame may cover our faces, that we have</hi> walked after as men: <hi>but henceforth our aime it ſo to</hi> walke as becometh the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cauſe it is of griefe to our ſoules, that there ſhould be Oppoſitions between our</hi> Brethren <hi>and</hi> us, <hi>when the</hi> Canaanite (i. <hi>depreſſing Merchants) and the</hi> breach-making Perizite, <hi>are in the Land,</hi> Gen. 13. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The truth is, after long ſeeking our</hi> God, <hi>and oft diſcuſſing with our</hi> Brethren, <hi>we peaceably ſet upon</hi> Reformation, <hi>Practiſing what we were convinced was</hi> moſt agreeable to the Word of God: <hi>Our</hi> Brother began <hi>againſt us:</hi> Printing <hi>againſt this our practiſe: Yet we forbore long, till we ſaw, that by our ſilence, not onely</hi> we, <hi>but</hi> Truth <hi>ſuffered; then were we</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>to print Our juſt</hi> Defence of ſundry Poſitions. <hi>And had</hi> he <hi>there ſtaied,</hi> we <hi>had, now, abode ſilent, who by printing this, may each of us ſeeme</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, imprudent, (<hi>as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaid oft of himſelfe, being forced ſo to write in his owne, and the Truths</hi> Defence, 2. Cor. 12. 11. <hi>&amp; 11. And truely, had it been our</hi> perſons <hi>onely that ſuffered, (though therein we ſhare deeply) by this Late Printed</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>with certaine Queries (being for an</hi> Anſwer to our Defence;) <hi>we had in this kinde held our peace; (although our</hi> Brother <hi>could not eaſily repaire our</hi> Damage.) <hi>But ſeeing</hi> Truth <hi>now ſuffers a</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>time, by our ſo</hi> long forbearing, <hi>we are againe</hi> enforced <hi>to this ſeeming</hi> folly <hi>or imprudence. And by our viewing and pondering our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> angry <hi>bitter expreſſions, if we in any paſſage ſeeme to any, to have</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>ſome of</hi> his wayes; (<hi>which we confeſſe we are ſubject unto,</hi> Pro. 22. 25.) <hi>Let our weakeneſſe remaine with</hi> us, <hi>and not be charged on the</hi> Cauſe, <hi>or Truth that we maintaine. We are learning</hi> not to render evill for evill, or railing for railing, 1 Pet. 3. 9. <hi>and hope we ſhall more fully be</hi> taught <hi>of God therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtian Reader, <hi>If thou haſt read our Brothers</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>we intreat thee to have</hi> one eare <hi>for this</hi> our Anſwer <hi>thereto: remembring what the</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>ſaid;</hi> He that is firſt in his owne cauſe, <hi>ſeemeth</hi> juſt: but his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour cometh and ſearcheth him, Prov. 18. 17. Conſider what is ſaid, and the Lord give thee <hi>and us,</hi> underſtanding in all things. 2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 7. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="response">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159806:3"/>
            <head>THE DEFENCE <hi>OF</hi> Sundry Poſitions and Scriptures, for the Congregational-way JUSTIFYED:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and beloved Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have ſaluted us with a querulous and Apologeticall Epiſtle; a querulous in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to us, and Apologeticall in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to your ſelfe; And with an 112 Queries, to all which you require us to give rationall and ſcripturall Anſwers; We will firſt take your Epiſtle into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and afterwards debate what is meete to be ſaid in reference to your Queries.</p>
            <p>And firſt we will conſider the juſtneſſe of thoſe charges that you lay upon us. Secondly, Whether you have acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your ſelf from thoſe charges you ſay are laid upon you.</p>
            <p>The charges you make againſt us may be referred to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we unjuſtly charge you of provoking us to be your Antagoniſt in print. pag. 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there is a difference betwixt our Title page and the text. pag. 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159806:4"/>3. That our pretending to prove ſome poſitions, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by other ſcriptures and arguments as to your intent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the preface, is a by-matter. pag 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That we doe not anſwer directly, but obliquely and evadingly. pag 10, 11.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we diſcover too much willingneſſe to quarrell at your expreſſions. pag 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That contrary to rule and reaſon when we ſhould make good the proofe of the Poſition from the Text alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, we call to you to prove the contrary. pag. 12</p>
            <p n="7">7. That we curtall and clip your anſwers, fold them up in obſcure &amp;c. Omit that which we know to be more perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, while we tranſcribe and largely anſwer ſome thing leſſe pertinent. pag. 13.</p>
            <p>To beginne with the firſt: How doe you acquit your ſelfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> from provoking us to be your Antagoniſts in print? Did the Booke breake forth into the world againſt your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? Your ſelfe imply the contrary, when you ſay others (rather then your ſelfe) thought fit the examination &amp;c. ſhould be printed. And what charge ſoever you gave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the prefixing of your name; yet we could not be ignorant what by <hi>R: H: M: A:</hi> of <hi>Maygd.</hi> Col. <hi>Cambr.</hi> meant. Yet it was not your name (which we love as we doe your perſon) that could provoke us, but the matter in the Booke; which as it tended to the ſubverſion of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which is in our apprehenſions ſutable to the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den rule of the word of God, and the ſetting up of another governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which in the things in controverſie we can ſee no other ground for, ſave humane policy and prudence, (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,) meaſured by the line of naturall reaſon: ſo it reflected upon us in ſome particulars, which falling from us in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or writing you took up, and committed your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto them to be made publique. And for that cauſe when we ſaw no other of better abilities take up the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we thought we were bound to make our defence as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159806:4"/> publique. But as <hi>Joſeph</hi> in another caſe ſaid to his Brethren,<note place="margin">Gen. 45. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Be not grieved that ye ſold mee, &amp;c:</hi> ſo whether you provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or whether we without cauſe were provoked, yet if God (as we hope he will) make this a meanes to bolt out ſome truth of his, ſo farre forth we ſhall rejoyce in it.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond charge is, that there is a difference betwixt our Title page and the Text (pag 7, 8.) for ſay you. <hi>The Title ſpeakes indefinitely, that the Poſitions and Scriptures al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged (not ſome or many of them) by me examined, are ſufficient, pertinent and full of power, and are manifeſted, yea clearely mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted ſo to be. But in your text you diſclaime the places applyed to Poſition 23, as it is by me controverted and are confident they are not found in the workes of any Congregationall man, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw 1. The title page was not that we ſent up, but was prefixed to our defence by a Friend, to whoſe care we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it, to ſee to the printing of it, our ſelves living at ſuch diſtance. And if leſſe had beene given out in the Title, it would not have derogated from the validity of the worke, and would have liked us better. Notwithſtanding we doubt not but to maintaine the concordance betwixt the Text and it, though not perhaps in every <hi>Punctilio.</hi> Yet it muſt be underſtood, that <hi>ſo farre as the Poſitions and ſcriptures are ours, and truly and juſtly alledged by you as ours, ſo farre we maintaine the ſufficiency and pertinency of them.</hi> And alſo ſo farre as Congregationall men have intended to make uſe of them, in reference to their true and proper ſcope, in alledging them, they are full of power, for they have produced and mentioned ſeverall of them as probable, and there is ſtrength of probability though not of certainty, even in thoſe texts in which the infallibility of them is not aſſerted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>title</hi> that we ſent up prefixed to our Booke, you may behold it in the firſt page of our defence without varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and we ſuppoſe you will judge it modeſt enough.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And whatſoever may be ſaid for the reſt, yet ſure we are, in the inſtance you give there is no difference betwixt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159806:5"/> them. For the Title page ingageth to <hi>a defence of ſundry Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and ſcriptures alledged to juſtifie the Congregationall way;</hi> But <hi>Poſition</hi> 23 as it is by you controverted, is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine deviſed by <hi>your ſelfe,</hi> and the ſcriptures fixed by your ſelfe, to render us odious to all other Churches and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saints. As for us, we hate and deteſt the thought of confining the Prieſtly, Propheticall, and Kingly Offices of Chriſt, to Churches meerely Congregationall; Neither were theſe ſcriptures ever alledged by us, or any of our judgement, (to our knowledge) to any ſuch purpoſe: therefore without claſhing with our <hi>Title</hi> page, we might and ought to explode them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Foraſmuch as your <hi>Title</hi> page runnes thus, <hi>The exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of ſundry ſcriptures alleadged by our Brethren in defence of ſome particulars of their way:</hi> Either make it out that ſome Brethren of the Congregationall way, have made uſe of theſe ſcriptures to this purpoſe, or elſe there will be found not onely an imaginary, but a reall claſhing betwixt your ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle page and your text, and you alſo will be found guilty the ſecond time, of a grievous reproach, not onely againſt the Brethren, but againſt the way it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond place, viz. <hi>Poſition</hi> the 15, wherein ſay <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> you, <hi>After the allegation of ſome Authorities inſtead of anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Text (upon which the diſtinction of Paſtors and Teachers is grounded) You, (the one a Teacher and the other a Paſtor) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, if we doe put a falſe gloſſe upon the ſcripture by miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Eph. 4. 11. yet more modeſt language (let any man finde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſty in that examination if he can) had become you Brother, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch reverend and learned men (whom your ſelfe honour) have gone before us in this expoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If we had only urged their authorities, you might have charged us with not making out in this place what we pretend in our title Page: but we urge and improve the reaſons, and ſo make them our owne reaſons, for the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of your anſwer. Firſt, after we have ſhewed that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159806:5"/> you tranſlate the prepoſitive article <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſome,</hi> or <hi>theſe,</hi> you gaine nothing by it; we endeavour to prove that the Doctors are not Schoole-Doctors, but Church Doctors, from <hi>Rom. 12. 7, 8. 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 8. and then proceed to prove that theſe Church Doctors are diſtinct from Church Paſtors, not onely by the authority of <hi>Zanchy,</hi> but by the reaſons rendred by <hi>Pareus</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> and ſpecified by us, viz. That God gives diſtinct gifts to Paſtors from thoſe that he gives to Teachers: For to the one is given a ſpeciall faculty of exhortation, to the other a clearer underſtanding of doctrine, and conſequently they are diſtinct offices; And yet you would make all men beleeve, that in our Reply, we defend not the Text at all.</p>
            <p>Concerning our concluſion, in which immodeſt language is charged upon you, and your defence of your ſelfe (<hi>Let any man finde immodeſty in that examination if he can</hi>) we ſay, we conceive not our ſelves injurious in it at all. For the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt language, though it be not in the examination of this Poſition, yet we finde it in the firſt words of the preface which is applicable in your proper ſcope, to all the poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo conſequently to this Poſition, viz. <hi>True Poſitions and lawfull practiſes muſt not (much leſſe untrue and unlawfull) be fathered upon God by miſinterpretation of his word, &amp;c.</hi> In which words you doe inſinuate the Poſitions which you examine, and practiſes built upon them to be untrue and unlawfull, and to be fathered on God by miſinterpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods word. And therein you doe not aſperſe us onely, but lay an immodeſt charge upon <hi>Bucer, Zanchy, Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who concurre with us in our Poſition and interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſay you, <hi>Doe you clearly manifeſt that the text Mat.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 18. <hi>(whatſoever other texts doe) doth prove that the Church muſt be Congregationall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We clearely manifeſt, what in conference we have endeavoured to prove out of theſe words, and the Poſition
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159806:6"/> as you have laid it downe and doe controvert it, we ſhall beleeve to be your owne Fiction, till you produce your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. We hold that the exerciſe of Church Power by the Congregationall Church is founded upon this text, as the obſervation of the Chriſtian Sabboth is upon the fourth Commandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. We have clearely proved that Chriſt in this place ſends the offended Brother to the Church endowed with power at that time when the offence ſhould be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and therfore ſends the Brethren of the Jewiſh Church to the Jewiſh. Church, whilſt that Church remained in power: and ſends the brethren of Chriſtian Churches in the times of the Goſpell to Congregationall Churches as they ſtand in oppoſition to Claſſicall, Provinciall, Nationall and Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenicall Churches. And how ſlight ſoever you make of this our Reply, except by ſcripturall reaſons, you force us to quit this ground, you loſe your Presbyterian cauſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſay you, <hi>Poſition the 20. Have you clearely mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>that the Keys were given to Peter to be uſed by him, (For you could not but know that to be the meaning) as a Diſciple, Beleever, not an Officer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have clearely proved the contrary; And yet you without the leaſt refutation of the proofe made by us, ſticke to the concluſion, <hi>that we cannot but know the meaning to be, that the Keys were given to Peter to be uſed by him as a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, or a Beleever, not as an Officer.</hi> A doctrine which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe againſt (as in our Reply we manifeſt) as neither conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the mind of the holy Ghoſt, (as we conceive) nor the Elders of New England, whom you alledge, as we proved it out of the ſenſe of their owne words. Doe we but ſing to a deafe man in what we ſay to you? We leave it to the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Reader to judge betwixt us.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, ſay you, <hi>Have you clearely manifeſted that Col. 4. 17. proves the Churches power to cenſure her Officers: when the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt argument you bring, to prove Archippus his faultineſse, without which it was no cenſure, amounts but to a ſtrong preſumption and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159806:6"/> that you know is but a weake proofe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A man would imagine that you (Brother) never built any concluſions as mortally probable upon premiſſes that might beget ſtrong preſumptions, but that all your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments were <hi>demonſtrationes potiſsimae,</hi> and concluded with an <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe you finde fault with our ſtrong preſumptions built upon two good reaſons, and uſhered in by the authority of <hi>Zanchy,</hi> as one of thoſe many Claſſick Authors that aſſert the ſame thing with us in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Yet your ſelfe upon this place argue thus. <hi>Paul</hi> (ſay<note place="margin">Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in pag. 15, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> you) bids <hi>Timothy fulfill his miniſtery, 2 Tim.</hi> 4, 5. yet <hi>this doth not ſuppoſe Timothy to be faulty, &amp;c.</hi> And then you adde, <hi>And it may be Archippus was not faulty, and then this Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was no cenſure.</hi> and thence you inferre, <hi>therefore its al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to no purpoſe;</hi> It had beene more tollerable if you had ſaid <hi>therefore it may be, it is alledged to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o purpoſe.</hi> Is it a <hi>fault</hi> in us to build a ſtrong preſumption upon two reaſons, yet uncontrowled? Is it <hi>no fault</hi> in you (Sir) to build a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory concluſion upon that which amounts to no more then an <hi>it may be,</hi> which is not ſo much as a remote probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, much leſſe a ſtrong preſumption?</p>
            <p>Since our worke and buſineſſe was to <hi>defend</hi> the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alleadged againſt your <hi>examinations,</hi> we have fulfilled what our Title page undertakes, if we prove <hi>that a Church hath a priviledge to admoniſh her Officers by virtue of this text,</hi> any thing in your examinations notwithſtanding. Now the two reaſons by us alleadged make it abſolutely cleare, that <hi>Archippus</hi> was faulty by virtue of <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 17. and that tho Churches power in <hi>cenſuring</hi> her Officers, may be, and is founded hereupon. <hi>i. e.</hi> For ought you alleadge to the contrary in that place, and containe in them grounds of a <hi>ſtrong preſumption</hi> that the thing is ſo indeede.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Have you (ſay you) <hi>clearely manifeſted from Adams Family, that 7 8 or 9, make a Church, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is not our worke to defend the Poſition againſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159806:7"/> your arguments? Is there any thing that hath the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of an argument produced by you in this ſection, which we have not fully anſwered? If there be, produce it.</p>
            <p>We thought it ſuperfluous and impertinent to prove that which your ſelfe clearely grant, when you ſay the caſe of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> was extraordinary, there were no more in the world, and therefore could be no more in the Church: Doe you not grant a Church at that time conſiſting of 7, 8 or 9, Of this we make uſe, and argue in effect thus; How few ever made a Church ſince the beginning of the world, the ſame may make a Church at this day: But 7, 8 or 9 (ſay you) <hi>made a Church in Adams time and Noahs time,</hi> Therefore 7 8 or 9, may make a Church at this day. Yet we would not have the Church to conſiſt of no more, but judge a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous addition of members a great mercy.</p>
            <p>As for our conceſſion (<hi>that God hath not preciſely determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned what number doth make a Church</hi>) which you make uſe of to darken the cleareneſſe of our manifeſtation, we ſay, It is a confirmation of our argument which we bring, viz. <hi>That looke how few have made a Church, ſo few may make a Church ſtill, becauſe God hath not determined what number a Church muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of.</hi> And it is brought to cleare the Poſition that 7 8 or 9, may now make a Church, becauſe ſo many have made a Church in <hi>Adams</hi> and <hi>Noahs</hi> dayes. And till you have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowne the ſtrength of the Argument which is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe words (<hi>becauſe God hath not determined what number muſt make a Church</hi>) you deale not candidly, to ſuggeſt that out owne acknowledgement in thoſe words, is againſt that cleare manifeſtation of that Poſition, which we in the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle page ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>Methinks you have not cleared</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. 8. 8, 9. is ſufficient and full of power againſt ſetled Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sir, It falls out with the beſt writers, as it doth with the beſt builders, they have not onely in the making of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159806:7"/> their walles certaine peeces of timber, which beare up the weight of the ſtories and roofe which if they were removed the whole building would fall; but alſo certaine carved en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteiſes, which ſerve for ornament, and yet poſſibly may yeeld ſome contributions of ſtrength alſo; yet ſo, that if they ſhould be removed, the building would remaine firme. Theſe amongſt the learned are uſually types, doubtfull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, and darke propheſies, which they bring in when they have ſolidly proved a point by ſound argument before. Thus it falls out with the Elders of New England, who being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded whether they did allow or thinke fit to allow and ſettle any certaine ſtinted maintenance upon the Miniſters, anſwer that there is nothing done that way amongſt them, and their practiſe they defend by two reaſons, which muſt needes inferre the unfitneſſe of the contrary courſe at leaſt to them which may be reſolved into theſe two Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Arg<hi rend="sup">•</hi>If the Condition of the Miniſters and the Churches to which they belong may vary, then it is unfit to ſettle a certaine and ſtinted maintenance for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: But &amp;c. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Arg<hi rend="sup">t</hi> If Chriſt our Lord hath appointed no ſuch thing as ſtinted maintenance, then it is unfit for the Church to ſettle ſtinted maintenance: But &amp;c. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe two pillars is the fabrike of their practiſe borne up; yet to adde ſome probable luſtre to what was well proved before, they adde the opinion of ſome Divines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Revel.</hi> 8. 8, 9. and they ſpeake doubtfully of the place, as not thinking it fit confidently to lay this burden upon it; But ſay they, <hi>if thoſe writers be not deceived, which ſo expound that ſcripture, as for our parts we know not but they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it truly, &amp;c.</hi> They ſay not confidently that the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is true, but that they know not the contrary; and if it be ſo, then it may be truly gathered, that the bringing in of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led endowments and eminent preferments into the Church hath beene the corruptions and to ſome t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deſtruction of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159806:8"/> ſuch as lived by them, both Church Officers and members. And we have endeavoured to ſhew the probability of this interpretation, but dare not ſpeake definitively of it. Yet the Poſition in the leter of it undertakes no more than what you (Brother) grant, viz. that <hi>Revel.</hi> 8. 8, 9. is applyed by ſome good Authors to thoſe times in which <hi>Conſtantine</hi> brought ſetled endowments into the Church, and yet we are ſtill beaten as though what the Elders intended (<hi>viz.</hi> to caſt a probable luſtre upon what was ſolidly proved before) we had not clearely delivered this text of ſcripture, and by conſequence muſt be guilty of belying God, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting the King of Kings hand, which is the language of the preface, and ſo make us a laughing ſtock to ſome, and the objects of hatred to other vulgar readers; For this cauſe we muſt of neceſſity diſcover your dealing in this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſaid of <hi>Amaleck</hi> that he met <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the way, <hi>and</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>ſmot the hindermoſt of them, even all that were feeble behind them:</hi> ſo you (Brother) ſhew a ſingular dexterity in paſſing by the two fore-mentioned reaſons, and fall upon the probable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawne from this place, the hindermoſt and moſt feeble of all the reſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againe, what they ſpeake <hi>hypothetically,</hi> and by way of ſuppoſition, you make uſe of <hi>thetically,</hi> and by way of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo, that it may well leave the ordinary reader under this apprehenſion, that we have no other argument to build our diſlike of ſtinted Church maintenance upon, but this place. For your ſcope is apparently not onely to vindicate the ſcriptures from abuſe, but alſo to confute theſe poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Congregationall way.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Once more, whereas the Elders ſhew that this place is applyed to thoſe times wherein <hi>Conſtantine</hi> brought ſetled endowments into the Church with <hi>ampla praedia large poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> you (Brother) leave out <hi>ampla praedia,</hi> and mention onely <hi>ſetled maintenance,</hi> whereas the place may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the latter ſenſe, as well as in the former. For there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159806:8"/> were certaine Revenues belonging to the Churches before<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> lib. 10. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtanſtine</hi> his time, as may appeare out of the imperiall conſtitution, directed to <hi>Anilinus,</hi> wherein he ſaith, We have already decreed the ſame, that the poſſeſſions belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Churches aforetime, ſhould be reſtored; And againe provide, that if either gardens or houſes, or other poſſeſſions whatſoever have belonged to the tytle of their Churches, all the ſame be ſpeedily reſtored to them againe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Give us leave to tell you, that we conceive you are not a little injurious to the <hi>Elders of New-England,</hi> and learned Maſter <hi>Forbes</hi> and others, whileſt you affirme that <hi>Conſtantines</hi> donation (as you ſeeme to underſtand it) <hi>is the foundation of this expoſition;</hi> becauſe you would imply, that they beleeve ſuch a donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to be a truth, which is ſuch an impudent fiction, that all wiſe men no ſooner heare it, but abhorre it. For thoſe which ſay<note place="margin">d. c. fund. de El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. Sext. Chro. vol. 2.</note> leaſt, affirme that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> gave the City of <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter</hi> the Pope and his ſucceſſours, and others are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to avouch that he gave all the <hi>Weſterne</hi> Empire. And this <hi>donation</hi> is mentioned by <hi>Gratian</hi> in the <hi>Decretalls,</hi> this alſo is cenſured by <hi>Nauclerus</hi> to be but <hi>Palea,</hi> becauſe it is manifeſt that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> gave <hi>Italy</hi> and other Kingdomes of the Weſt to his ſonnes by his laſt will and teſtament. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not of this <hi>Donation</hi> but of other maintenance which <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> beſtowed; not upon the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> alone, but upon other godly Biſhops and Miniſters throughout his Empire, are the <hi>Elders of New-England</hi> Maſter <hi>Forbes</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>Eightly ſay you, <hi>And Poſition 7 doe you manifeſtly cleare that 2 Cor, 8, 5. doth pertinently and powerfully prove, that every member at his admiſsion doth promiſe to give himſelfe to the Church to be guided by them, when you ſay, the practiſe of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Macedonia is by way of alluſion made uſe of, and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is a Comparatis. For you know alluſions and compariſons are not argumentative.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:159806:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why doe you the <hi>ſecond time</hi> after admonition gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by us in our former booke leave out that, without which neither can the Churches directing, nor the members fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing direction be lawfull. For the <hi>Elders of New-England</hi> ſay not that a Church member is to give himſelfe up to the Church to be guided by her according to <hi>will,</hi> but according to <hi>God;</hi> But theſe words (<hi>according to God</hi>) you leave out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If to anſwer all your <hi>Reaſons</hi> to the contrary be to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this <hi>Poſition</hi> by vertue of this <hi>text,</hi> we have done it; produce (if you can) any thing which hath the leaſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of an Argument in it, which we have not anſwered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We have ſhewed that the caſe of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Churches, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5. is <hi>paralell</hi> with the caſe of a member giving himſelfe up to be guided by the Church according to God: For as God gave <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> to direct the Churches of <hi>Macedonia</hi> according to God, ſo God hath given particular Churches to direct their ſeverall members according to God, that is to ſay, The Elders by way of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice authoritatively, and the brethren as God ſhall give them opportunity to adviſe and admoniſh their fellow mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Therefore by the ſame reaſon that the Churches of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> gave themſelves up to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> by the ſame reaſon ought Church members to give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to the Church to be directed by her according to God.</p>
            <p>But you would make men (at leaſt if any poſſibly may looke upon this exception, as though Logique Reaſon and Religion what ever they be are wholy in ſubſerviency to your preſent deſigne) beleeve (whether you have confuted us or no) that we have conſuted our ſelves, when we ſay it is <hi>Argumentum a comparatis;</hi> for ſay you, <hi>You know that alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and compariſons are not argumentative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For unleſſe we muſt unknow all that we have knowne to gratifie your cauſe withall, we muſt needes profeſſe that when we were but boyes in the Univerſity, we were taught that one head or common place from which Arguments
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159806:9"/> were to be drawne was a <hi>Comparatis</hi> from Comparriſons. And we have had no reaſon to extirminate that doctrine from intermedling with the matters of God. Suppoſe a man ſhould ſay to Maſter <hi>Hollinworth</hi> (a Miniſter) <hi>You ſhould ſeaſon others with the ſalt of knowledge, and of the love and ſeare of God, for you are the ſalt of the earth, Math. 5. 13. You ſhould feede your people with wholeſome doctrine and diſcipline, for you are a ſhepheard,</hi> would Maſter <hi>Hollinworth</hi> out with this Logique, and ſay <hi>Comparriſons prove nothing</hi> and therefore the Arguments are naught? Did <hi>Paul</hi> commit a <hi>ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> in <hi>Logique</hi> when he proves that <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould receive maintenance becauſe <hi>the mouth of the Oxe muſt not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>zelled, that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> treadeth out the corne?</hi> Or is our Saviours argument weake and inſufficient, when <hi>he juſtifieth his Diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for plucking the eares of corne,</hi> by an argument <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Comparatis</hi> taken <hi>from Davids taking and eating the ſhew-bread?</hi> So that, till we have ſomething more then your bare aſſertion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us, we ſhall beleeve there is a truth in the old rule of <hi>Analogie, Quod de uno, ſecundum proporti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem affirmatur vel negatur, id etiam de altero: That which is aſſerted or denyed of one thing, according to proportion may be aſſerted or denyed of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing.</hi> And if you can overthrow this old maxime, we are confident that the <hi>Claſsique</hi> cauſe will ſuffer as well as the <hi>Congregationall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, ſay you, <hi>In stead of cleare manifeſtation of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters mantenance out of the stock of the Church, you ſay, we thinke we ſee moſt warrant for it from the New Teſtament, and as moſt probable once diſputed it, but neither then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What ſhall our modeſty be now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de uſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us? Though it be ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet we ſhall deſire to be mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<note place="margin">Saluſt. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Jug.</note> ſtill. It was the Commendation of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that he did <hi>plurimum fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qui;</hi> We hope God will never leave us ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelves as to profeſſe my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> practiſe confidently and per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159806:10"/> as of divine inſpiration or inſtitution, for which we have not a <hi>cleare</hi> evidence of ſcripture; That tythes and ſtinted Church maintenance are unlawfull, that Miniſters are to be maintained out of the Church ſtocke, the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtribution whereof appertaineth to the Deacons office, we conceive we have ſolidly proved out of the word of God: But that the Miniſters are to be maintained by ſuch a ſtocke as is raiſed by a <hi>weekely contribution,</hi> becauſe it is not <hi>abſolutely</hi> cleare in the Text (at leaſt to us) we thought fit to diſpute it onely as <hi>probable.</hi> If you could come as neare unto a demonſtration of <hi>Claſsique</hi> goverment, as this chapter doth to a demonſtration of a ſtocke by week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribution of the Church, and we had no more to ſay againſt it, then yet we have heard (for we cannot propheſie what you may hereafter produce, againſt a Stocke raiſed by weekely contributions, we ſhould be tender how we mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd a word againſt <hi>Claſsique</hi> government.</p>
            <p>2. Except you can produce ſome one of the <hi>Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall</hi> way, that in writing or diſputation hath aſſerted week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contributions to be of divine inſtitution, and binding to all Churches, we ſhall eſteeme the <hi>Poſition</hi> and ſcripture annexed (as to ſuch a purpoſe) your owne invention. As for us as we defended it in diſputation, ſo we have to the ſame purpoſe clearely manifeſted it to be ſufficient, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and full of power, viz. to make it <hi>probable,</hi> that the Miniſtery ſhould be maintained by a Stock raiſed by week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contributions, and ſee no cauſe to doubt, but that we have ſolidly anſwered all your arguments to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Colophonis vice,</hi> as the cloſe of this charge, you conclude when you ſay, <hi>we thinke we conceive its probable, and doe never ſo confidently aſſert any of the ſeverall Poſitions, and do not prove the ſame by the ſeverall texts reſpectively alleadged, nor cleare the ſaid text from all Objections made againſt your Expoſition (one materiall Objection unanſwered being enough to invalidate the ſame) you afford ſo many Arguments to any wiſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159806:10"/> Reader, that you have not clearely manifeſted the Poſitions and Scriptures where ſuch Speeches are found to be ſufficient, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All that we have to ſay is this, Firſt, That <hi>your triumph</hi> concerning our not proving the <hi>Poſitions</hi> by the Text reſpectively alleadged <hi>is before your victory.</hi> Secondly, Though one materiall Objection unanſwered (unanſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you ſhould ſay, for our weakeneſſe may not (peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) be able to defend a truth) doth invalidate <hi>our Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> yet where we urge divers Texts to any Poſition, if any one of them be truly urged, and ſo unanſwerable, though you ſhould invalidate all the reſt as to ſuch a purpoſe, you may advantage the truth thereby, but advantage not your cauſe at all. So that one materiall Objection (ſuch as we have not yet met with in your writings) though it might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate the <hi>Expoſition,</hi> yet poſſibly might not prejudice the <hi>Poſition</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third Charge</hi> which you lay upon us, that our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending <hi>to prove ſome Poſitions and practiſes by other Scriptures and Arguments (as to your intent expreſſed in the preface) is but a By-matter, For Poſitions and practiſes may be true and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and yet not truly and lawfully grounded on the Text allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When the King had burnt <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> Rowle, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 32.</note> and he cauſed <hi>Baruch</hi> to write the Rowle a new, it is ſaid, <hi>he added beſides to them many like words.</hi> If we had neglected to anſwer your <hi>Examination</hi> of the ſcriptures alleadged by us, and had fallen upon <hi>new ſcriptures,</hi> you might well have complained: but we thought <hi>good meaſure preſſed downe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together and running over,</hi> would not have offended you. And yet the truth is, we know not how to pleaſe you, the one way or the other. In ſome ſections (though to our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding) we have not left any thing in the ſimilitude of an <hi>Argument</hi> unanſwered yet) we are complained of, that we have <hi>not clearely manifeſted the Poſition,</hi> as we have already ſhewed. And how ſhould this be done otherwiſe than by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159806:11"/> anſwering your <hi>Examination,</hi> unleſſe it be by new <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> And what are <hi>Arguments</hi> worth, if not backed with <hi>ſcriptures?</hi> and yet when beſides our anſwer to your exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, we adde ſome ſhort diſſertation upon the Point, this is counted as a <hi>By matter</hi> to your <hi>intent</hi> in the preface.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your <hi>intent</hi> as it appeares both in your <hi>Tytle Page,</hi> the <hi>Preface</hi> and the <hi>Booke</hi> it ſelfe, was not onely to vindicate the <hi>ſcriptures,</hi> but to diſcover the ſuppoſed weakneſſe of the <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> contained in the <hi>Poſitions.</hi> And why ſhould not we as well aſſert the <hi>doctrine,</hi> as vindicate the <hi>ſcriptures,</hi> which (ſome of them cull'd out by you) are the weakeſt and moſt feeble parts of the proofe made by us as we have told you</p>
            <p n="3">3. You could wiſh you ſay, <hi>We might keepe cloſe to the Scriptures and Poſitions alleadged, till they be one way or other cleared, and then we may more orderly proceede to other ſcriptures and arguments:</hi> and yet you that cannot <hi>endure</hi> any addition of ſcripture or reaſon applyed to the queſtion ſtated more fully to our <hi>owne</hi> ſenſe, than they are in the Poſitions drawn up by <hi>you,</hi> require us in the meane time to give ſcripturall and rationall anſwers to no leſſe then an hundred and twelve <hi>Queres,</hi> whereof ſome of them are <hi>Nihil ad Rhombum</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants (we are aſſured) in the buſineſſe of controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betwixt us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth Charge</hi> that you make againſt us, is, <hi>That we doe not anſwer directly, but obliquely and evadingly in ſundry places, as where</hi> (ſay you) <hi>I alledge that the Apoſtles never taught or practiſed to gather or ſeparate one part of this true Church, and and another part of that, eſpecially perſons whom themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted not, to make a purer Church. You anſwer of another thing which was never denyed, viz. The Apoſtles both taught and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſeparating of ſome Jewes from other Jewes and gathered them into a Chriſtian Church, while yet the Jewiſh Church was not diſsolved, but was a Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are ſo farre from anſwering <hi>obliquely</hi> or <hi>eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly</hi> in this place, that we dare be bold to ſay, that no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159806:11"/> can more <hi>front</hi> and <hi>diametrically oppoſe</hi> ſuch a confuſed anſwer as yours i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, then this of ours doth. We did obſerve that the ſuppoſed <hi>strength</hi> of your anſwer, was couched in the <hi>four ſinewes</hi> of it. 1. We thought you deſerted it as a thing diſſonant to the doctrine and practiſe of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to gather ſome Chriſtians from others to make a purer Church. 2. We conceived that the truth of the Churches from which perſons are gathered, was that which you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, made the gathering of them in ſuch ſort to beare no conformity with the Apoſtles doctrine or practiſe; And we conceived there was this implication in it, that it might be lawfull and ſuteable to the doctrine and practiſe of the Apoſtles, to gather beleevers out of a <hi>falſe</hi> Church, but not out of a <hi>true.</hi> 3. We conſidered that this might have ſome ſtrength in your thoughts, that there is no ſuch thing men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the doctrine and practiſe of the Apoſtles as the gathering of <hi>one Church</hi> out of <hi>many.</hi> 4. That you imagined that there was ſome ſtrength in it to prove <hi>our gathering</hi> of Churches unlawfull, becauſe the perſons gathered were ſuch as we <hi>converted not.</hi> Having thus <hi>anatomized</hi> in our thoughts your Anſwer, we addreſſed our ſelves to diſcover the weakneſſe and fallibleneſſe of all theſe <hi>Exceptions,</hi> and we began with the <hi>ſecond,</hi> becauſe it was moſt <hi>generall;</hi> and ſo deſcended to the reſt which were more <hi>particular.</hi> And <hi>Firſt,</hi> we ſhewed, that the <hi>truth</hi> of a Church is not that that can make it ſinfull or <hi>unlawfull</hi> to gather or take in the members of it into the union of <hi>other</hi> Churches; For then it ſhould have beene unlawfull for the <hi>Primitive</hi> Churches to have gathered in the beleeving <hi>Jewes</hi> into their Churches whileſt that Church remained <hi>true;</hi> But this ſay we was the doctrine and practiſe of the Apoſtles. Now what can be more <hi>point blanck oppoſite</hi> to this part of your anſwer then this? Hence alſo our concluſion hath the ſtrength of this argument in it, If it be not <hi>unlawfull</hi> to withdraw from <hi>one</hi> Church that is <hi>true,</hi> then it is not <hi>unlawfull</hi> to gather out of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159806:12"/> twenty or an hundred, i. e. becauſe they are <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>this was not a Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We conſider it not as <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> but under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>truth,</hi> as it was a <hi>true</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. Nor are the Reformed Churches and Miniſters to be compared with the then Jewiſh Church and Prieſts thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You ſhuffle in the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the one, and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the other impertinently: We have onely to doe with the <hi>Churches,</hi> and we ſay the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches might be compared with the then <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we conſider it in, viz. in point of <hi>truth;</hi> For the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church was a <hi>true</hi> Church as well as the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. It was but one</hi> (ſay you) <hi>and you ſhould ſhew gathering out of ſeverall Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doe we not ſhew it thus? If it be lawfull to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of <hi>one</hi> true Church, then it is lawfull (upon the ſame ground) to gather out of <hi>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>the Apoſtles gathering was onely of thoſe Jewes they converted to Chriſtianity from unconverted Jewes, and you ſhould ſhew the gathering of Chriſtians conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by others, from other Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This alſo <hi>we have</hi> ſhewed at large, clearing alſo the former <hi>objection</hi> together with it by ſeverall arguments and two places of ſcripture, viz. 1 <hi>Cor. 5, 6. 2 Cor.</hi> 13, 10. In our ſecond, third, fourth, fift, and ſixt particulars, and theſe in oppoſition to the firſt and third particulars where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we thought you placed the ſtrength of your anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. But you ſhould ſhew the gathering of Chriſtians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by others from other Chriſtians converted as well as they, and poſsibly from thoſe perſons by whom they were converted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And this we have fully cleared, pag. 10. from the practiſe of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>None but an <hi>Emperick</hi> would cenſure a <hi>Phyſician</hi> that he doth not cure all diſeafes with <hi>one</hi> Doſſe. Shall our <hi>reply</hi> be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159806:12"/> judged <hi>oblique,</hi> evading, &amp; inſufficient, becauſe it is not a buſh to ſtop <hi>every gap</hi> with, though it be moſt punctually oppoſite to that part of your anſwer, againſt which we levelled it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that Church was then by Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to be diſſolved, and many Churches to be built upon its ruins, and therefore doth no more warrant the building of one Chriſtian Church upon the ruine of other Chriſtian Churches, than the Parliaments Commiſsion (if there were ſuch a one) to the Inhabitants of Derby hundred, to take downe Lathamhouſe to build them houſes of, doth warrant any one of the Inhabitants to take as many good stones as they can come by, out of this, and that, and the other neighbours houſe, concerning which they gave no ſuch Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You lately found fault with an argument of ours, becauſe it was <hi>a Comparatis,</hi> alleadging that alluſions and Compariſons are not <hi>argumentative,</hi> if alluſions and Compariſons were not capable of a better <hi>ſymmetrie</hi> and proportion then this of yours, we ſhould not onely not yeeld them to be <hi>argumentative,</hi> but we ſhould diſavow and diſcard them as not <hi>illuſtrative.</hi> For though it was not our intent (as we ſaid) to anſwer <hi>all the branches</hi> of your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, with this one inſtance, but onely that that deceives its ſtrength from the <hi>truth</hi> of Churches (and therefore your <hi>triumph</hi> out-running your <hi>victory,</hi> might well have beene ſpared, when you ſay, <hi>your not bringing a more punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and more pertinent proofe, argues either an implicite confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the truth of my anſwer, or inability to oppoſe it</hi>) and though we have brought other punctuall and pertinent proofes which are above the reach of your inſtance, yet though all were as you would beare the world in hand, your <hi>Allegorie</hi> wants that due proportion that ſhould render it <hi>illuſtrative,</hi> much more <hi>argumentative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Firſt, it is not the practiſe of <hi>Congregationall</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or Churches, to take <hi>any,</hi> much leſſe <hi>as many</hi> good members as they <hi>can</hi> come by out of this, and that, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159806:13"/> other neighbouring Churches, concerning which, God hath given no Command that thoſe perſons ſhould leave thoſe Churches. For ſo your compariſon ſhould be framed to make it runne <hi>paralell</hi> with the caſe. Nay the <hi>Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall</hi> members make it their ſcope to take in none but thoſe, that having righteouſly withdrawne themſelves from other Churches, doe voluntarily tender themſelves to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, that ſo they may enjoy thoſe Ordinances purely with the corruption of which they were not onely polluted, but endangered before; And that they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy other Ordinances <hi>purchaſed</hi> for their ſpeciall edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the precious <hi>bloud</hi> of Chriſt, which their ſoules lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in the want of, whileſt they were (ſome of them) as members in the line of <hi>Parochiall-Communication.</hi> Once more, it is the ſcope and end of <hi>Congregationall</hi> members, and Churches (if we underſtand them aright) ſure we are, it is our owne deſire and practiſe, to receive in no mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but from ſuch Churches, in which we have no ground of hope in ſight, for a <hi>reformation</hi> in any tollerable propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time, all of us having expreſſed the <hi>offence</hi> given us by <hi>Parochiall</hi> diſorders to <hi>private</hi> brethren, becauſe it would have beene interpreted a diſturbance of the Churches peace, for private perſons to ſpeake <hi>publiquely</hi> againſt the received practiſe of the Church; And ſome of us who by our calling were better enabled, having not onely in vaine witneſſed againſt the Leaven, with which we ſaw the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches leavened, but alſo fruitleſly waited a long time for redreſſe of preſent greivances, when there was no hope left, have withdrawne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>God</hi> by meanes of this preſent happy <hi>Parliament,</hi> (wherein next under God is our preſent hope) or by other ſhould worke <hi>ſuch</hi> a reformation, that we might comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably joyne with Churches meeting neerer to our habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then our owne, we ſhould be willing for our parts (and we beleeve the ſame of all our brethren) to lay downe by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159806:13"/> mutuall conſent our <hi>Covenant,</hi> and fall into fellowſhip in ſeverall other Churches, eſpecially where we were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times members reſpectively.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It ſuppoſeth the Churches from which our members have withdrawne, have as good right to hold their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as well as any man in <hi>Derby hundred</hi> hath to with-hold the ſtones of his houſe from thoſe that without a juſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er endeavour to take them away; which how you will make out, ſeeing that you hold no other tie, but the boundaries and limits of the <hi>Pariſh</hi> or <hi>Chappelry,</hi> do ſo fervently diſpute againſt expreſſe agreements and <hi>Covenants</hi> we underſtand not. Yet if the waies and walking of <hi>Pariſh</hi> Churches were ſuch as tended to the edification of the members, and no juſt cauſe appeare of their removall or withdrawing, we ſhould not conteſt with you about it. But if either viſible wicked members be admitted to the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> without hope of redreſſe, or the diſpenſation of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and execution of the <hi>power of the Keys,</hi> and other <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> be wanting, without hope of redreſſe, we conceive they have no more power to with-hold ſuch a member from joyning to another Church for his ſpirituall better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, than a <hi>Maſter</hi> hath to with-hold his <hi>Servant</hi> from removing to another <hi>Family,</hi> that ſo he may not be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled by being ſtraitned in his food, or endangered by the unwholſomeneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, But it may be there may be ſome more ground for your <hi>fift charge,</hi> which is, <hi>That we diſcover too much wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to quarrell at your expreſsions: a little after</hi> (ſay you) <hi>you diſcover too much willingneſſe to quarrell at my expresfions, wherein you ſay I would ſuggeſt, that you make oppoſition to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy: but doth not Maſter</hi> Weld <hi>a Congregationall man, when Maſter</hi> Rathband <hi>chargeth Independents to hold, that Chriſtians may and ought to ſet up new Churches and practiſe in them all Gods Ordinances without the conſent of a Chriſtian State, yea againſt their peremptory Commands and eſtabliſhed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159806:14"/> lawes, and in the midſt and againſt the minde of ſuch Churches, as they freely acknowledg to be the true Churches of God, ſay of this Article, no pen can expreſſe a greater latitude of oppoſition againſt Magiſtracy and Lawes, and Churches too, then he affirmes to be in us? Doe not I uſe his owne words? Print them in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Character? Cite them in the Margent? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, you do ſo; notwithſtanding it was not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned by us, and the fault was <hi>moſt</hi> in your ſelfe; For you print it in a different Character, and cite Maſter <hi>Weld</hi> in the Margent, but were defective in a letter to guide to the citation: and hence the miſtake: For you cite <hi>Anſwer to 9 poſ.</hi> pag. 76. as appertaining to the letter (<hi>U</hi>) ſpeaking of ſomething that was proper to <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> men, and then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately joyne <hi>T. W.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> pag. 67. by cloſe to it, without any other letter, as if it had belonged to the ſame thing; and ſo we received of it, as you may diſcerne by our <hi>defence,</hi> when we make any mention of that part of your anſwer, which ſpeakes of the Apoſtles preaching againſt the peremptory Command of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> we print your Citation pointed at by the letter (<hi>b</hi>) and we annexe <hi>T. W.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> pag. 67. to it, as appertaining to the ſame thing. The truth is, we were faulty alſo, becauſe if we could have looked into that place of Maſter <hi>Welds</hi> booke, we might have rcctified our ſelves in that miſtake. But <hi>that Booke</hi> was out of our way, when we <hi>ſhould</hi> have done it, and afterwards we did not minde. And as for the <hi>different</hi> Character, we minded it leſſe, becauſe for many cauſes the Character is changed, beſides that when other mens words are cited. Had we beene aware that they were Maſter <hi>Welds</hi> words, we would have have given a more pertinent anſwer, which hereafter if there ſhall be occaſion we ſhall annexe.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>this is but one example of many,</hi> as we know <hi>none</hi> at all, ſo if there be <hi>any</hi> of moment, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelves we ſhould have met with them under his charge, for you ſpare not to give many inſtances of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159806:14"/> ſame kinde, when you apprehend it makes for your advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>ſixth charge</hi> undertakes to prove that <hi>we have a ſacul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and make much uſe of it to turne the proofe over to you. When I ſhew you</hi> (ſay you) <hi>where the proofe of the Poſition, from the text alledged is defective, and require you to ſupply that defect, you then turne it over to me to prove the contrary, as 1 Cor. 16. 1. When I ſay the Churches of Galatia might for ought you alledge to the contrary, be combined one to another, the ſubſtance of your anſwer is, without proofe we connot grant it; And that you may more plaufibly put the buſineſſe off your ſelves, you leave out the words (for ought you alledge to the contrary</hi>).</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A little beſore we were told that to prove ſome poſitions by other ſcriptures and arguments than thoſe annexed to the Poſitions (as to your intent in the preface) was a <hi>by matter;</hi> And it was wiſhed that we might keepe cloſe to thoſe ſcriptures and poſitions till they were cleared, but in this place though we <hi>anſwer</hi> your <hi>arguments,</hi> and conſequently make good the proofes annexed, and when we have done, tell you that without proofe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not grant ſuch a <hi>Claſſicall</hi> Combination in <hi>Galatia,</hi> as is in <hi>Scot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and in <hi>Holland,</hi> yet we are arraigned as departing from rule and reaſon, becauſe we turne the probative part over unto you. Is not our part <hi>defenſive</hi> onely of theſe <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and ſcriptures?</hi> And if we deliver the <hi>ſcriptures</hi> of the doctrine contained in the <hi>Poſitions,</hi> any thing in your <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations</hi> contained notwithſtanding, we doe <hi>Sportamquam nacti ſumus ornare,</hi> Performe what we have undertaken. And though when we doe more, (if ſolidly and truely) your ſelfe and all the lovers of truth are ſo much the more our deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, yet if we doe thus much onely, you have no cauſe to enſure us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for you, Foraſmuch as you afford ſuch hard quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Poſitions</hi> as to make them by interpretation a <hi>helping of God, counterfeiting of the King of Kings hand, and an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159806:15"/> addition to his word,</hi> (ſince he that makes a charge muſt prove it) we thought you were bound (theſe <hi>arguments</hi> in your <hi>examination</hi> failing) either to make out your <hi>charge</hi> by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>arguments,</hi> or at leaſt confeſſe, that you have wronged the <hi>Authors</hi> of ſuch <hi>Poſitions</hi> and the <hi>truth</hi> it ſelfe, and therefore we put you upon <hi>proofe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As we put nothing <hi>off</hi> our ſelves that belonged to us, ſo we never left out thoſe words, (<hi>for ought you alledge to the contrary</hi>) for any ſuch end as you ſuggeſt. But for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſake, and becauſe we thought there was nothing mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall to the buſineſſe in hand, either for your advantage, or our diſadvantage contained in them. For though if you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it in a ſenſe nothing to the purpoſe, viz. <hi>The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Galatia might be combined, for ought we alledge to the contrary;</hi> meaning God could have combined them, ſo he could have made <hi>Rome, Paris,</hi> or <hi>Madrid,</hi> the place of an <hi>Oecumenicall Congregation,</hi> for worſhip and government; It is true: yet if you meane the Churches of <hi>Galatia</hi> might be combined, for ought we alledge to the contrary, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>there is nothing in the proofe made in the Poſition that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres the non<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> combination of the Churches of Galatia:</hi> we ſay, it is your overſight to aſſert it. And we turne not over the <hi>proofe</hi> to you, but having confuted the ſuppoſed <hi>proofe</hi> to the contrary, vve ſend you to ſeeke <hi>new arguments,</hi> or yeeld us the cauſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>laſt charge,</hi> is of a <hi>great wrong</hi> to your ſelfe, and the truth of God, (as you ſay) viz. <hi>That we curtall and clip your anſwers and arguments, not onely the ſupplement, but the ſubſtance and ſtrength of them, folding them up in obſcure, &amp;c. ſometimes omitting them with a Cenſure;</hi> You aske us a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you not omit that which you know to be pertinent, while you tranſcribe and largely anſwer ſomething leſſe pertinent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What may be done through overſight vve knovv not, but vve have omitted nothing <hi>pertinent</hi> of purpofe or adviſedly; <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus late<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in generalibus,</hi> your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en generall char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159806:15"/> we cannot but take to be great injuries, and the iſſues of a ſpirit of <hi>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raction,</hi> ſince you would beare the world in hand, that they are ſo <hi>many,</hi> that they would too much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large this Epiſtle, augmenting it in ſundry <hi>pages;</hi> If you had ſpared your <hi>Queries</hi> at this time, and left roome for the diſcovery of theſe ſuppoſed <hi>unc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndide</hi> paſſages, you had done your <hi>ſelfe</hi> no leſſe <hi>right,</hi> and <hi>us</hi> much leſſe <hi>wrong;</hi> And if you had but barely cited the pages and lines where ſuch paſſages are found, would this have ſwell'd up your Epiſtle to many pages more?</p>
            <p>But let us conſider the <hi>inſtance</hi> you give, and leave the Reader to gueſſe at the reſt, for its more then probable, you would ſingle out the groſſeſt you could finde.</p>
            <p>And firſt, concerning the omitting of the ſeven parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, in <hi>poſition</hi> 24. Which you plainely affirme <hi>we left out, leaſt the Reader had we ſubſcribed them ſhould have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anſwer.</hi> We rendred another <hi>reaſon</hi> (which we have the cleare teſtimony of our conſciences for, was the true reaſon why we left them out) and that which you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no reaſon at all) yet as though you did communicate with God, in his incommunicable excellency of being <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſearcher of the heart,</hi> you affirme, that <hi>thereſore</hi> we left them out, <hi>least the Reader (had we tranſcribed them) ſhould have expected an anſwer.</hi> We ſay againe, if we give you for granted thoſe ſeven <hi>particulars,</hi> (or rather ſeven <hi>generall heads,</hi> including in them many particulars) improve you them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the beſt advantage of your <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> cauſe, in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the doctrine included in the 24 <hi>poſition.</hi> For thoſe particulars how many ſoever they be, are no parts of the <hi>diſcipline</hi> left by Chriſt to the Church, which (the <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſaith) in the eſſentials of it is unchangeable, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>poſition</hi> may be defended, though thoſe particulars be granted. And for this cauſe we ſhall deſire to be excuſed with you, and nothing feare, incurring prejudice with the Reader, though we did not tranſcribe your ſeven <hi>tedious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies</hi> to the cauſe in hand.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:159806:16"/>
            <p>2. We ſay further, in that we tranſcribed them not, we rather ſpared <hi>you</hi> then advantaged <hi>our ſelves;</hi> for there is ſomething in all of them, that is either doubtfull or juſtly liable to exceptions.</p>
            <p>For you (undertaking to ſhew the differences betweene the Apoſtolicke Churches and ours) ſay:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Jewiſh Ceremonies were then ſcarce dead, at least not buried, hence we are not bound to circumciſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We anſwer,</hi> This Legall right of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was never on foot among the Apoſtolick gentile Churches, nor were they bound any more to it then we are now, therefore there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no difference in that, betwixt us and the primitive Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke gentile Churches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The civill cuſtome of thoſe Countries differ much from ours, hence we are not bound to make the covering of a mans head, a token of diſhonour, 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 4, 5. 7. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> What ever it be that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> meaneth by <hi>covering of the head,</hi> (for that is diſputable) it ſeemeth to us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be <hi>perpetuall and binding to all Churches</hi> as well as to that of <hi>Corinth,</hi> becauſe of the Apoſtles <hi>reaſons</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 7. 14. He ſaith <hi>ver. 7. The man ought not to cover the head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the Image and glory of God, but the woman muſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is the glory of the man.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 14. he ſaith, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe teacheth, that if a man have long haire, it is a ſhame to him, becauſe haire is not given to him for a covering.</hi> (For ſo it is to be underſtood to make the <hi>Antitheſis</hi> perfect) <hi>But if a woman have long haire, it is an honour to her, becauſe her h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire is given her for a covering.</hi> We think the reaſon is fetcht from the <hi>excellency</hi> of the one ſexe above the other, and that reaſon which is drawne from <hi>nature,</hi> are <hi>perpetuall,</hi> And if ever in force, remaine <hi>ſtill in force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Church was then but in gathering from amongſt Heathens and Jewes, bence we want examples (to convince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory. Anabaptiſts) of the baptizing of Chriſtian Infants, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such an argument as this, you uſe to defend your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159806:16"/> ſelves, in pleading for an <hi>Nationall</hi> Church, Scripture (ſay you) mentioneth not a <hi>Nationall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Church; for beleevers were not ſo many then, as to beare the name of a Kingdome or Nation. As we conceived it weake againſt us, ſo may the Anabaptiſts judge it unſatisfactory againſt them. For can any one rationally thinke, but that among thoſe many <hi>thouſands</hi> converted of Jewes and Heathens, and gathered into Chriſtian Churches, there were not many who had Infant Children, ſome of them borne before they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, who upon ſuch converſion of their parents were to be accounted Chriſtian Infants, and others borne after ſuch converſion in that period of time, which the hiſtory of the Acts of the Apoſtles fills up, which Infants muſt alſo be ſtiled <hi>Chriſtian Infants?</hi> And if ſo, then the reaſon of wanting examples of baptizing Chriſtian Infants is not that which you alledge, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the Church was then but in gathering from amongſt the <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Jewes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But becauſe it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt (for what cauſe we dare not determine) <hi>to forbeare the expreſse menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning of Infants baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Church was then under heatheniſh perſecuting Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, hence they had no houſes built for or appropriated to holy worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In your <hi>Examinations</hi> pag. 6. you cite, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 22. and ſay, <hi>To come together</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is, (<hi>if rightly tranſlated) to come together in one place, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Eccleſia is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the buildings or houſes in which they did eate and drinke in:</hi> Here you ſay, <hi>That the primitive Churches had not hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp;c.</hi> Doe you not manifeſtly <hi>contradict</hi> your ſelfe? for if they were not houſes, in which they did eate and drinke in, but did meete together in for holy worſhip, were they not ſo farre forth ſet a part for holy worſhip?</p>
            <p>If by <hi>appropriation of houſes to holy worſhip</hi> (which you ſay <hi>was not then in the primitive times,</hi> but <hi>ought to be now</hi>) you meane ſuch a ſetting a part as muſt neceſſarily exclude all uſing of ſuch houſes to other purpoſes, it is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:159806:17"/> 
               <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> ſo to conceive or ſpeake. But if you grant that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe may be made of them otherwiſe then in Gods worſhip, How are they then <hi>appropriated</hi> to Gods worſhip more now then in the times of primitive Churches? For they were then knowne noted places, (at leaſt among ſome Churches) and capacious of great multitudes, in which the Churches did ordinarily meete, as from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 23. appeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They meete in the night to pray, preach and celebrate the Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And did they not meet in the day alſo? How elſe did<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 23</note> the unbeleevers meet with them &amp; come among them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miniſters had no ſetled maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is a <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> that becauſe the Church was under <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> and perſecuting Magiſtrates, therefore Miniſters had no ſetled maintenance. Is there any rule for ſetled maintenance in the whole Goſpell? which yet (being that there are predictions many, of peaceable and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous times to the Church) there might have beene, if God had meant any ſuch thing. Nay, there are intimations, (if not cleare declarations) againſt ſetled maintenance to ariſe from the Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was then an extraordinary effuſſion of the Holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, and ſundry of the Elders and people; hence there was no neede of Univerſities, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes: there was neede, becauſe you ſpeake but of ſundry, and the Apoſtle deſired that they all might ſpeake <hi>with tongues,</hi> but rather that they might <hi>propheſie, 1 Cor.</hi> 14. 5. therefore there might be uſe of ſchooles in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to them that wanted extraordinary gifts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor of studying for Sermons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes: Elſe what meaneth the Apoſtle when he bids <hi>Timothy stirre up the gift, &amp;c.</hi> and give attendance to reading, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No uſing ſet Prayers and Pſalmes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Were there no ſet Pſalmes in thoſe dayes? were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159806:17"/> thoſe Pſalmes, Hymmes, and ſpirituall ſongs, which the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and at <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> and all the Churches did ſing inſpired by the ſpirit? And were no ſcripture Pſalmes ſung in thoſe times? That will be a ſtrengthening to them that doubt of the ſinging of <hi>Davids Pſalmes.</hi> As for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, is there a neceſſity now of a Forme, becauſe extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts are ceaſed? May not an ordinary gift be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently helpfull, to put up prayers by? We would thinke it ſhould now be unſeaſonable to plead for ſet formes of prayer.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The Apoſtles had the care of all the Churches, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difference taught and baptized, and ordered matters in all Churches where they came, now we may not expect ſuch Officers, but muſt be content with ordinary Elders, amongſt whom ſo much of their power as God intended to be perpetuall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s divided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if there be an univerſall viſible governing Church which you plead for, the <hi>Elders</hi> of it muſt have care of all the Churches, and muſt Preach, Baptize, and rule where ever they come. And the <hi>repreſentative oecumenicall Church</hi> or Counſell conſiſts of ſuch Elders that every of them muſt have care of all the Churches. Where then is the difference according to your principles betwixt the Apoſtles and ſuch Elders in that matter? And whether the Brethren do not ſhare in ſome of their power you know is under controverſie.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>There were then ſome extraordinary occaſionall precepts, and practiſes which binde not in ordinary, as ſelling all to give to the poore, Mat. 19. 21. having all things common, Act. 2. 44, 45. &amp;</hi> 4. 32. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 35.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Selling all and giving to the poore,</hi> was never a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept nor practiſe in the Chriſtian Apoſtolike Churches; nor doth <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 21. prove it, whereas you produce it to declare the difference betwixt the Apoſtolike Churches and ours. The <hi>having of all things common,</hi> had not any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept for it in the Apoſtles dayes that we know of, and the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:159806:18"/> practiſe was voluntary and not binding, though ſome did it, they freely did it, and others were not bound to follow, as from <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 4. appeares. Where then is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Apoſtolike Churches and <hi>ours?</hi> For were there now like cauſe, for having all worldly ſubſtance <hi>common,</hi> and ſhould God incline the hearts of Chriſtians thereto, it might be lawfull <hi>now</hi> as well as then.</p>
            <p>Now (Brother) we have given you an account what wee are able to ſay to your Seven Particulars, which we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted before. And whether we did hurt you to helpe our ſelves by our former ſilence of them, let the intelligent <hi>Reader</hi> judge.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond inſtance is,</hi> out of your <hi>Examination</hi> of your <hi>Poſition</hi> the Sixt, where you ſay, <hi>a maine paſſage is omitted without giving any hint or intimation of any thing omitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Printer, or he that copied it out for the Preſſe, poſſibly hath omitted an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will it be worth the <hi>roſting</hi> what you have taken in <hi>hunting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. We might chalenge you if you can, ſo to avoide the <hi>whole,</hi> or any part of thoſe ſix lines omitted, to the releefe or reſcue either of the cauſe or your <hi>Examination,</hi> as they relate unto the <hi>Poſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thoſe words wherein you alledge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 9, 10. we looked upon them as free of the Company of thoſe By-matters you beſought us in the Preface not to meddle with; which if we had examined, could neither advantage your cauſe nor indanger ours.</p>
            <p>For the reſt of the words omitted, they are but different expreſſions of the ſame thing imported in the words tranſcribed and both fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>You ſay (but it is your miſtake) <hi>That the Covenant (Gen. 17) is taken for Gods part of the Covenant or Promiſe to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gal. 3. 16, 17. Not for mans part to God,</hi> whereof we no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak, &amp; then adde <hi>Gods Covenanting with Abraham</hi> did not impoſe nor ſuppoſe <hi>an expreſſe vocall Covenant on Abrahams
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159806:18"/> part.</hi> Now if this be ſo, then was not <hi>Abraham</hi> bound to any thing on his part by vertue of this Covenant; but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is manifeſt from <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. where God ſaid to <hi>Abraham, Thou ſhalt keepe my Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If it be ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>This Covenant was Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Circumciſion is called the <hi>Covenant</hi> Metonymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, as the <hi>Seale</hi> may be called by the name of the thing <hi>ſealed;</hi> and therefore is called the <hi>token</hi> of the Covenant, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If it be ſaid, <hi>this was not an expreſse vocall Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Poſition</hi> mentioneth an holy Covenant, but ſaith nothing of an expreſſe vocall Covenant; and you by your bringing in theſe words do alter the Queſtion; nor doe we hold an expreſſe vocall Covenant neceſſary to the being of a Church. And we would be rightly underſtood, when we ſay it is neceſſary to the <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> of a Church. Our meaning is not, that it is a ſtanding Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, that the Church ſhould be united by a <hi>vocall expreſsion</hi> of their mutuall conſent (which we call the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>) ſo as that <hi>ſubſcription, ſignalls,</hi> or <hi>ſilence</hi> it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as a <hi>ſigne,</hi> may not be a lawfull teſtification of their conſent: but that for as much as with <hi>the heart man beleeveth to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and with the mouth confeſsion is made unto ſalvation;</hi> for as much as God hath given us our <hi>tongues</hi> to expreſſe our conceptions withall, it is fit and convenient, that it ſhould be expreſſed in words, and ſo words are neceſſary, as one (and uſually the fitteſt) expreſſion of our mindes.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, having proved, that the ſtipulation 'twixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>mutuall,</hi> you are rather our debtor than we yours; for paſſing by your expreſſions concerning <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 9, 10. as <hi>expletive</hi> to fill up your ſentence upon a juſt period, rather then <hi>argumentative,</hi> for would i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be an intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inconſequence thus to argue.</p>
            <p>If Gods covenanting with a creature doth not alway ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſo much as an implicite covenant on the creatures
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:159806:19"/> part, then Gods covenanting with <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. doth not ſuppoſe an expreſſe vocall Covenant on <hi>Abrahams</hi> part; (take it at the beſt as you have ſtated it for your advantage, quite beſides the queſtion.)</p>
            <p>But the firſt is true, <hi>Gen. 9. 9, 10. Ergo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c.</hi> For what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders though it doth alwayes doe it, why it may not doe it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. Beſides the Aſſumption may be called in queſtion in point of truth. If you ſpeake of a Covenant, as properly ſo called: For whereas you urge that the birdes and beaſts could not ſo much as give an implicite aſſent, we ſay it is true: but ſay withall that it was not a Covenant in propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of ſpeech with them, but improperly, even as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant mentioned, <hi>Job 5. 23. Hoſ.</hi> 2. 18. And we ſay with Maſter <hi>Rivet, In foeder is objecto quaeri poteſt, an animalia ſunt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rivet in Gen 9.</note> 
               <hi>foederis capacia, quae neque ſtipulari poſſunt, neque promittere, ex ſuperioribus id repetendum quemadmodum indirecte, &amp;c.</hi> In the object of the Covenant it may be enquired how living creatures can be capable of the Covenant, which can neither ſtipulate nor promiſe. Therefore we muſt repeate what we have ſaid before, that as the living creatures became ſharers of the puniſhment of ſinne, indirectly and for mans ſake, ſo the benefit of the Covenant concerning the not ſending of another flood doth indirectly and for mans ſake, belong unto them. So for children not borne, it was no actuall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but onely vertuall and potentiall, to the reduction of which into an actually mutuall Covenant, (which is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant properly ſo called) was required the ſtipulation of the Children, when they ſhould be actually called, to take hold of Gods Covenant.</p>
            <p>But this Covenant as it related to <hi>Noah,</hi> did ſuppoſe a Covenant on <hi>Noahs</hi> part. For he was bound to faith, and walking with God on his part, as well as God to preſerve him and the world from a flood. For as Maſter <hi>Rivet</hi> ſaith upon another occaſion, <hi>Fiunt autem foedera mutua ſtipulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one partuum, &amp;c. Covenants are made with a mutuall and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:159806:19"/> ſtipulation, of engaging themſelves to the performance of ſuch and ſuch benefits and duties.</hi> Here we reade of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of a mercy on Gods part, but there is no mention of the duties that <hi>Noah</hi> for his part was to performe, but yet this muſt be underſtood that <hi>Noah</hi> would walke juſtly and uprightly as he had done in former times. So <hi>Paraeus</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this place calls it, <hi>mutuum foedus, a mutuall covenant.</hi> So that if it be underſtood of a Covenant properly ſo called, and <hi>homogeneall</hi> with that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. (and if it be not, the argument will be of no force) it may be ſaid that Gods co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting with man, doth ſuppoſe a reſtipulation or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant on mans part.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third inſtance</hi> is out of <hi>poſition</hi> 7. where alſo you would have the Reader to underſtand; that the chiefe part of your anſwer, viz. <hi>It is not ſaid they gave themſelves to the Church or Churches, but to us, viz. Paul a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Timothy, is left without the leaſt limit or intimation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are not theſe words to be found in our <hi>defence?</hi> pag. 44. <hi>The argument is fetcht</hi> a Comparatis, <hi>the members of the Churches of Macedonia did as much in a like caſe: they gave themſelves to the Lord, and to the Apoſtle and Timothy, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods will, to be guided by the Lord, and directed by them, a whole Church or Churches to one or two perſons gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And an argument is fetcht thence thus, then may one perſon that is to joyne to a Church, as fitly give himſelfe to the Lord to be guided by him, and to the whole Church and Officers thereof to be directed by them according to the will of God.</hi> Doe not we grant, that it is not ſaid, that they gave themſelves to the Church or Churches, but to us, viz. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy?</hi> Nor doth the Poſition imply any other thing. For it ſaith, <hi>As the members of the Church of Macedonia did in a paralell or like caſe.</hi> It ſpeakes onely of ſomething done pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to that which they preſſe: where then is the injury done to you? Is it in this, that without mentioning <hi>your allegation,</hi> as your allegation, we have yet anſwered
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159806:20"/> the whole ſtrength of it? Forgive us this wrong, and retract your charge, which though it have truth in it, in the letter of your words in which it runs, yet it wants truth in your <hi>ſcope</hi> in which you make it; For you complaine of <hi>wrong</hi> to <hi>you</hi> and the <hi>truth of God,</hi> but cauſeleſly and moſt injuriouſly, as from what is preſented is manifeſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth inſtance</hi> is out of <hi>Poſition</hi> 22, where you ſay, <hi>Your whole anſwer to Revel. 4. 4. is by an Index expurgatorius blotted out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have ſought up our papers, and we perceive that in the copying out of the <hi>Reply</hi> for the preſſe, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this text was omitted, <hi>Caſu an Conſilio,</hi> we cannot ſay. The anſwer was to this effect, it hath been uſually the practiſe of men of the moſt approved parts, and unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned integrity, after they have ſolidly proved a place by plaine texts of ſcipture, then to adde as probable thoſe which in their judgement lookt that way, though more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, as typicall and propheticall places; The ſame is that practiſe of the Elders of <hi>New England,</hi> in urging this place. So that if you could make it out, that the Elders have miſt the genuine ſenſe of the place, yet you have but knockt off one of the <hi>Emblemata</hi> of the garniſhings of the roome, whereas the Poſition it ſelfe remaines unſhaken by you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We doe profeſſe our ſelves unwilling to defend the <hi>poſition</hi> by vertue of the text (at leaſt in that expreſſion, viz. <hi>of authority and governing power</hi>) yet it may be thoſe reverend learned and religious Authors are able to maintaine it, though we by reaſon of our weakeneſſe dare not undertake it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As for the expoſition that you put upon it, though it be conſonant to the interpretation of ſome learned wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and though it ſeemed probable to one of us, yet upon further inexpectation, though we abſolutely reject it, we have not yet theſe exceptions againſt it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:159806:20"/>1. We reade not of any eyes that the 24 Elders had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the four beaſts <hi>were full of eyes, Rev.</hi> 4. 8. Is this the meaning of it, that the Churches in the foure Quarters of the world <hi>had eyes,</hi> that is, wiſdome, knowledge, underſtanding to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, order, guide, and diſpoſe of the affaires of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: But the Officers wanted <hi>eyes,</hi> and ſo were excluded from directive power? For this will follow upon your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, at leaſt, if your argument againſt the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Elders of <hi>New England</hi> give of <hi>Crownes,</hi> prove ſolid. You ſay by their expoſition, <hi>The Elders which are ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the foure beaſts, are excluded from governing power, for they ſit not on Thrones, nor have Crownes on their heads.</hi> And we will ſay againſt you, the Elders which you would have to be the Elders of the Churches are excluded from dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power, for they have not <hi>eyes before and behinde,</hi> as the four beaſts have.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We reade that the four beaſts doe lead the four and twenty Elders in the worſhip and Service of God in the Church, <hi>Revel. 4. 9, 10. When thoſe Beaſts gave honour and glory, &amp;c. the four and twenty Elders fell downe and worſhipped, &amp;c.</hi> So alſo c. 5. 8. 11. 14. Now whether the <hi>Churches</hi> doe lead their <hi>Officers</hi> in all their worſhips they performe to God, (which will follow from your expoſition) or the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers</hi> doe lead the <hi>Churches,</hi> judge you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ſee no abſurdity in Maſters <hi>Cottons</hi> and <hi>New-Englands</hi> brethrens expoſition, who make the four <hi>beaſts</hi> to be the <hi>Officers</hi> of the Churches, and the four and twenty <hi>Elders</hi> to be the <hi>members.</hi> As for your allegation of <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. 9. 11. 13, 14. where you ſay, <hi>That the Elders are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from beleevers;</hi> We anſwer to it, We diſcerne not that the <hi>Elders</hi> are any more diſtinguiſhed then the four <hi>beaſts</hi> are, which yet you interpret to be the <hi>Beleevers</hi> of the four parts of the world, let the place be viewed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> drive, that by <hi>Crownes,</hi> are Enſignes of <hi>authority</hi> any more then <hi>white rayment</hi> was an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159806:21"/> Enſigne of <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> yet he aſſerts, that in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that belongs to Church members, which is the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Kings</hi> that weare Crownes: As 1. <hi>That they tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act nothing by themſelves, but by their Officers. 2. Their conſent</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cott.</hi> Caſe.</note> 
               <hi>is requifite to the judgements that paſſe in the Church.</hi> And therefore it may ſeeme leſſe ſtrange, if they appeare with Crownes.</p>
            <p>Having thus anſwered that part of your Epiſtle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you lay divers <hi>charges</hi> upon us, we ſhall now more brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwer the former part of your Epiſtle, wherein you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to purge your ſelfe from thoſe <hi>charges</hi> laid upon you. And you ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The deepe and heavy charge (as you call it) in the firſt part of my preface againſt miſinterpretation of ſcriptures, as a belying of God, counterfeiting the King of Kings hand, (though I now ſee how I have ſped) I re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>t not of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither appeares it that you doe repent, that you<note place="margin">Pſal. 35. 11.</note> have <hi>poſition</hi> 23 laid to our charge things that we knew not, yea things, that when we heard of them, were of <hi>deteſtable</hi> conſideration in our thoughts. If you ſhall ſolidly confute our <hi>reply,</hi> we ſhall juſtifie you in this impenitency, but if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, we ſhall deſire to <hi>mourne in ſecret</hi> for you, and <hi>pray,</hi> that God would give it an impreſſion upon your ſpirit.</p>
            <p>You have the more cauſe to <hi>repent,</hi> if that be true which you alledge in the <hi>portall</hi> of your <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> viz. <hi>that the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination &amp;c. was for the moſt part an anſwer to ſome allegations, as they were privately made to you for ſatisfaction.</hi> For doe doubting brethren wanting light addreſſe themſelves to you for ſatisfaction concerning the meaning of ſuch and ſuch ſcriptures, and doe you publiſh their <hi>doubts,</hi> as their <hi>poſitions,</hi> and what was propoſed to you <hi>privately</hi> to obtaine <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> doe you <hi>divulge</hi> it to the <hi>world:</hi> as <hi>a belying of God, a counterfeiting of the King of Kings hand, an addition to his Word?</hi> Surely this will make men tender how they ſeeke <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> from you for the future.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:159806:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor ſee I cauſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>why you ſhould repine at it, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of it: if you have clearely manifeſted (as in your title page you ſay you have) the poſitions and ſcriptures alledged for your Church way, and by me examined, to be ſufficient, pertinent, and full of power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not the meaning of this amount to thus much? (For undoubtedly theſe cenſures relate to the <hi>poſitions,</hi> and conſequently to the authors of them) that if an interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be clearly manifeſted to be ſufficient, pertinent, and full of power, then the perſons that give it, may not complaine, though they be all bedawbed with imputations of <hi>belying God, counterfeiting the King of Kings hand, adding to the Word?</hi> Muſt innocency of neceſſity be ſtupid and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of injuries?</p>
            <q>Dat veniam corvis, vexat cenſura columbas.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>And yet I find my ſelfe deeply charged by you to deprave pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, blotte and blurre ſweet, humble, ſpirited, holy, pertinent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, to wrong the Elders of New-England, wreſt allegations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let the Reader judge betwixt us, if it be not truth. But you goe on and ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea though I ſaid, I will not tell you who ſaid all the Church is holy, &amp;c: yet you thinke it not unworthy my ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether it might not be ſaid to mee, as ſometimes Chriſt ſaid to one of the twelve, when he asked, Master is it I? and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, thou haſt ſaid: (a bitter perſonall invective) &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We intended not theſe words as any invective at all, much leſſe as a perſonall invective as you affirme; It was never an <hi>Embrio</hi> in our thoughts to compare you with <hi>Judas</hi> (as you inſinuate) 'tis cleare as the Sun, that you compare the <hi>Congregationall members</hi> in the purſuit of their way, to <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi> Our meaning is plainely this, by this forme of ſpeaking, borrowed from our Saviours words in another caſe, to ſignifie that it might rather be ſaid againſt you, what you bring againſt us, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall governours doe take too much upon them,</hi> becauſe they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:159806:22"/> take upon them, an authoritative power over thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations over whom Chriſt hath not ſet them. Your reaſons to prove that our way is the <hi>gainſaying</hi> of <hi>Corah</hi> are weake: For 1. this <hi>ſchiſmaticall</hi> company would utterly have taken away the power of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſo when they had <hi>Officers,</hi> would have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their <hi>Officers:</hi> we onely in the extraordinary caſe of an utter want of an <hi>Elderſhip</hi> to ordaine, hold it fit to ordaine by perſons deputed, or by Elders elected; If in the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of a Church, there doe joyne as members, ſeverall perſons that have beene approved Miniſters, whilſt their relations to their ſeverall Churches were in being, then ſome of theſe are deputed to ordaine the <hi>firſt Elder;</hi> If there be but one Preacher joyned as a member, and ſeverall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of eminent holineſſe and gifts fitted for <hi>ruling Elders,</hi> then there is an <hi>Elderſhip</hi> choſen, and the reſt of the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ordained <hi>one</hi> of their Company for their <hi>firſt</hi> Elder. In the Church of <hi>Duckenfield</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> four Preachers joyned in the foundation of the Church. At <hi>Sourby</hi> in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> but one; But in both places the Ordination was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed either by Preachers as deputed, or by elect El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the placing of Church power in the body of the Congregation, were the gaineſaying of <hi>Corah,</hi> then becauſe election of Officers (<hi>Act.</hi> 6.) is a branch of Church-power, and was placed in, and acted by the body of the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that <hi>Church</hi> was guilty of the <hi>gaine-ſaying of Corah,</hi> which is your ſecond Argument.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis not true, that our cauſe enjoynes or allowes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining (<hi>i. e.</hi> of the regular exerciſe of the power) of the Elders that rule over them in the Lord, for taking too much upon them, but we honour and obey the <hi>Elderſhips</hi> of our ſeverall Churches; and alſo the Elders and Members deputed of ſeverall Churches met in a Synod occaſionally to rectifie diſorders, &amp;c. which the particular Churches
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:159806:22"/> are not able to accompliſh. But as for <hi>ſtated Claſsicall-El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhips,</hi> and your ſeverall <hi>graduall Judicatures,</hi> ſwallowing up the <hi>Votes</hi> of the <hi>Elders</hi> of the particular Congregation in the Major part of the <hi>Votes</hi> of the <hi>Synod,</hi> Ordaining, Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, Admoniſhing, Excommunicating, Reſtoring; we ſay, theſe are not powers ordained of God. And conſequently we are not guilty of the gaineſaying of <hi>Corah,</hi> though wee ſhould ſay of theſe, <hi>They take too much upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You proceed, <hi>The uſuall occaſion of your Cenſures of depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving places,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is a wide (I hope) not a willing miſtake in you, and not any iniquity in my hands or heart, you expect the Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Scriptures alledged, to agree fully and exactly with the places cited in the Margent, which I neither profeſſed nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We expect not an exact agreement in words and expreſſions, but yet we could not but looke for an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to the expreſſions of your Marginalls in ſenſe and importment. Where you ſay Poſition. <hi>See almoſt the ſame Argument verbatim.</hi> We expect with good cauſe an exact agreement in ſenſe and almoſt in words. When you ſay, <hi>See the like,</hi> we expect there an exact agreement in <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and a likeneſſe in manner of expreſſion, and ſo in the reſt. For if there be not the ſame thing aſſerted in both, the Margent is ridiculous. In divers Poſitions your Marginalls have no ſuch modifications in them, muſt we not expect an exact agreement in ſenſe and words in thoſe places?</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Marginalls</hi> themſelves are <hi>profeſsion</hi> enough of ſuch an agreement, eſpeciall to any man that readeth your Preface, where you ſay, <hi>The way of Independencie produceth ſundry texts in Preaching, Writing, Conference, which for the moſt part alſo, ſhe produceth in Print upon the ſame or the like occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not this import an agreement in ſenſe and import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, betwixt the <hi>Printed</hi> Bookes alledged and the <hi>Poſitions</hi> gathered from Preaching, Writing, Conference?</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:159806:23"/>
            <p>When you ſay, <hi>You alledge Printed Bookes probably to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate whence the Propoſition was taken:</hi> Do you not imply that the ſubſtance of the Propoſition is to be found in the place from whence it is taken, and if it be not found there, are you not juſtly to be blamed?</p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay <hi>The Printed Bookes alledged in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent are the By-ſtanders ſpoken of in the Preface,</hi> either we doe much miſtake you, or you doe, (which were ſtrange) not a little miſtake your ſelfe. What then is the meaning of theſe words in the Preface? <hi>I publiſh not all their Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor all that is materiall, but ſo much (as I conceive) at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſufficient. If any of the Brethren (amongſt whom Mr. Cotton is deſervedly the chiefe) ſeeme in my apprehenſion to come neerer the truth then others, I willingly take notice of it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> one among the reſt of thoſe Authors in <hi>Print,</hi> whoſe <hi>Depoſitions</hi> you publiſh, how then is Mr. <hi>Cotten</hi> and the reſt made <hi>By-ſtanders</hi> which muſt not be med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with? And (by the way) if you had any action at all to enter againſt the cauſe, vvhy did you ſo uningenuouſly as not to publiſh all that is <hi>materiall?</hi> Is it your meaning that you would have liberty to alledge our Printed Bookes at your pleaſure, and we might not take notice whether you did them right or wrong? This ſeemeth to be too groſſe. For our parts we tooke <hi>By-ſtanders</hi> and <hi>By-matters</hi> to be meant of ſome expreſſions rather of an <hi>ornative</hi> and <hi>exple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> then of an <hi>argumentative</hi> nature.</p>
            <p>The next thing you indeavour to purge yourſelfe from, is <hi>from affecting Prelacy, which you ſay, we doe ſecretly intimate,</hi> and that <hi>to this end, to caſt an odium upon you and the cauſe you plead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We know you are more wiſe then to expreſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to declining <hi>Prelacie.</hi> If you ſhould, this could not with rationall men, bring an <hi>Odium</hi> upon your Cauſe: and when you ſay, <hi>peradventure the word (ſimply) was put in for a retrect, in cauſe you ſhould be hotly purſued for pleading the Cauſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159806:23"/> of Prelacie under the notion of Presbytery;</hi> we intended to ſhew the weakneſſe of your reaſoning, not to caſt an <hi>Odium</hi> upon you, for the thing it ſelfe avoid the force of it if you can. If (you ſay) <hi>Diotrephes was not blamed for having prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence.</hi> Doe you not plead the Prelaticall Cauſe? And if you ſay, <hi>he was not ſimply blamed,</hi> Doe you not cleare the Allegation of the Elders? If there be any other place men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it, and we hope to give you ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>That you in the worſt times were not more Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall then the greateſt and godlieſt Independents in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if not at leaſt one of us have beene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For our ſelves, when we firſt entred into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, we were both of us <hi>conformable</hi> in <hi>judgement,</hi> and ſometimes (though very rarely) in <hi>practiſe.</hi> But we have bewailed, and publiquely teſtified our repentance, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and ſince the times of this preſent Parliament. The one of us renounced it, and was therefore <hi>ſuſpended</hi> by the <hi>Biſhop of Cheſter</hi> fourteene yeares agoe, and was afterwards about thirteene yeares ſince <hi>expulſed</hi> from his habitation, and after that about eleven yeares ſince was forced to leave the Kingdome, and to ſeeke for ſhelter in <hi>Holland,</hi> and there joyned with others in a <hi>Congregationall way,</hi> and after that when the unſutableneſſe of that aire occaſioned much ſickneſſe, he was conſtrained to returne, and finding no reſt was the ſecond time neceſſitated to tranſplant himſelfe into <hi>New-England,</hi> where if the <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> at <hi>Yorke</hi> could have let him alone, he might probably have ended his dayes; But for none appearance at their Courts, when yet he was out of the Land, and knew nothing of their ſummons, he was fined in ſeverall ſummes of money, which together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to fifteene hundred and fifty pound. And his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in <hi>Wirrall</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> was extended upon for payment, and the Tenant to whom the Land was leaſed beſore his departure to <hi>New-England,</hi> forced to pay great ſummes of money for the redemption of his cattell, which were driven
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:159806:24"/> off the ground: where he was ſupported in thoſe troublous times by the beneficence of two religious Gentlemen, <hi>viz.</hi> Maſter <hi>William Stevinton</hi> of <hi>Dothit,</hi> and his ſonne in law <hi>Creſwal Taylor</hi> of <hi>Longdon</hi> aforeſaid his noble friends. And the tidings of theſe cruell proceedings, and the greivous complaints of the Tenant, comming over to him in ſeverall letters, he was adviſed to try if by his returning backe, he could uſe meanes to free his eſtate, but beſore he arrived this renowned <hi>reforming Parliament</hi> was aſſembled, and what he hath ſuffered ſince for his oppoſition to <hi>Prelacy</hi> is known not to a few.</p>
            <p>As for the other of us, ſome yeares before the <hi>Biſhops</hi> fell, and whilſt their power ſeemed to be bound as with a Band of iron and braſſe, being enforced by the then Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of <hi>Hereford,</hi> to turne his afternoone Sermon into a Cateciſme Lecture. Upon that occaſion ſtudying more elabourately and induſtriouſly the ſecond Commandement, through the rich grace and mercy of God not onely ſaw the evill of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and ceremonies impoſed, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of the uſe of them, and publiquely in the Pariſh of <hi>Almele</hi> in <hi>Herefordſhire</hi> preached againſt them, and for all the ſubſtantials of that way of Congregationall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ever ſince, and at this day, he hath and doth judge to beare moſt conformity with the word of truth. Afterward being troubled in the Biſhops Court for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, and having no hope of liberty, did by conſent leave <hi>Almele,</hi> and lived about three yeares in a ſmall pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar exempt from Epiſcopall Juriſdiction, viz. <hi>Longdon</hi> upon <hi>Terene</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire.</hi> And yet we ſuppoſe there may be other Independents (ſo called) more anti-prelaticall then our ſelves. Concerning you, though you have forced us by your cauſeleſſe compariſon, (which alſo was a manifeſt charge) to appeare in our owne juſtification, yet (that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done) we are not willing to vent our ſelves in the words of detraction againſt you, but we leave you to your owne
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159806:24"/> conſcience to be judged; and to the judgement of ſome thouſands of perſons, who have many yeares been acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with your whole courſe of preaching and living, whether the <hi>compariſon</hi> was equall.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>You plead for the government of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches maintained by Maſter</hi> Burne <hi>of</hi> Mancheſter, <hi>Maſter</hi> Goſnall <hi>of</hi> Boulton, <hi>Maſter</hi> Fleetwood <hi>of</hi> Wigan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What theſe Reverend men did hold or maintaine, we have no particular knowledge, ſaving that we thinke good to let you underſtand, that Reverend Maſter <hi>Burne</hi> was in his latter dayes, in a great part againſt that <hi>Claſſicall</hi> way which you contend for. And we have notes of his <hi>owne hand</hi> writing, which we can if need require (and hereafter it may be ſhall) produce, to the open view of men. In which he cloſeth very much with the Brethren of <hi>N. England</hi> in their anſwer to the nine <hi>Poſitions,</hi> and diſlikes Mr. <hi>Bals Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Brother, we have endeavoured to take off the ſtrength of your complaints, which you make againſt us in your Epiſtle. Our hearts doe witneſſe for us that we inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to uſe guile or cunning craftineſſe in our defence of the Poſitions and Scriptures againſt your examinations, nor yet to aſperſe you with reproaches, but with integrity of ſpirit, what we have beleeved with the heart, we attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the maintenance of without any deſigne of wronging you, much leſſe the truth of God. We hope your ingenuity will be ſuch that you will retract ſo hard a cenſure, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of ſuch a cauſleſſe out-cry, with which you cloſe your Epiſtle. If not, let the godly intelligent Reader judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, whether we or the Complainant hath moſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as for us it ſhall be our deſire that peace &amp; truth may abound more and more with you, and with</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Brethren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sam. Eaton.</signed>
               <signed>Tim. Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:159806:25"/>
            <p>COncerning your queſtions, whereto you require ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and ſcripturall anſwers, you have beene ſo inſatiable in the multiplication of them, as that you have made your demand irrationall to rationall men. If ſeven or eight queſtions may well exerciſe an Aſſembly of men ſome weekes, perhaps monthes, to give ſcripturall and rationall anſwers to them, how long may one or two be exerciſed in anſwering one hundred and twelve queſtions?</p>
            <p>Yet we ſhall ſay ſomewhat to them, and give our ſenſe of them, the better to be excuſed with the Reader, though we give not at preſent a direct ſcripturall anſwer to any of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Your queſtions are reduceable to theſe heads. Some of them are either in whole or in part anſwered already, in our defence, as Q. 11. 24. 30, 31. 35, 36. 38. 41, 42, 43. 48, 49. 52. 56. 73. 77, 78. 84, 85. 102, 103.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some of them are bottomed upon miſtakes, of things aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted to be held by us, which yet we hold not, as 19, 20, 21, 22. 39. 44. 50, 51. 56, 57, 58. 61. 80.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some of them do ariſe and proceed <hi>ex non conceſſis,</hi> from things taken for granted, which yet we cannot grant, as 23. 29. 32. 84.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some of them are <hi>de non negatis,</hi> of things which we grant and yeeld as well as you, wherein you and we doe agree, or elſe they are <hi>de negatis,</hi> of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs which both you and we do alike deny, as 55. 86, 87. 91. 96, 97, 98, 99, 100. 102, 103.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Some of them are in the nature of them deep cenſures, &amp; full of calumny &amp; ſlander, both of our way &amp; perſons, as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. 10. 15. 37. 41. 45. 49.. 57<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 78. 83. 88. 104. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Some of them ſavour of a bitter diſtempered ſpirit, and tend to incenſe the Magiſtrate againſt us, as 57. 96. 106, 107, 108, 109, 110, 111, 112.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Some of them ſeeme to be dubious queſtions procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a troubled ſpirit, that either we have Auditors to heare us preach or any maintenance from any beſide them of our owne way, as 77. 79. 84.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:159806:25"/>8. Some of them are entrapping queſtions, and in them there is <hi>aliquid latens</hi> ſome thing that appeares not and you watch for advantage, as 76. 81. 82.</p>
            <p n="9">9. One of them (in a ſuperfluous Parentheſis) gibes at the language of many godly knowne Chriſtians, who yet are able to juſtifie their expreſſions, <hi>viz.</hi> 46.</p>
            <p n="10">10. One of them is a queſtion concluding with a vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious chalenge. <hi>viz.</hi> 100.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Some of them are ſuch as that many of the Brethren of the Presbyterian judgement doe agree with us in them, and we may referre you to them to anſwer them, as 46. 71.</p>
            <p n="12">12. One of them is rather a point controverted among your ſelves then betwixt you and us, <hi>viz.</hi> 90.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Some of them are impertinent and come not up to the controverſie betwixt us, as 16. 17. 18. 44. 54. and ſame others.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Some of them are unneceſſary queſtions, becauſe the anſwering of ſome one, would cut off and make voide the neceſſitie of propounding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and anſwering of the reſt of that nature, as the anſwering of the 7. would prevent the propounding of the 8. 10. 13, 14. the anſwreing of the 11. would make the 9. and 12. uſeleſſe. So the anſwering of 63. makes vaine the propounding of 58. 59. 60. 61. 62. 64. 65. 66. 68. and ſo of others.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The moſt of them are argumentative, and do diſpute againſt the thing, and ſometimes conclude peremptory, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then propound and inquire after the thing of which yet in forme of words there is a queſtion made.</p>
            <p>By all which it arpeares how many of this great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Queſtions might have beene ſpared, and how little reaſon we have to anſwer them.</p>
            <p>Had you not done more commendably if you had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſome one Queſtion of a kind; as namely, one about conſtitution of Churches; one about gathering out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches, one about the qualification of Members; one about an univerſall viſible governing Church; one about
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:159806:26"/> diverſity of Congregations in thoſe City Churches men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in Scripture; one about the entity and power of an incompleate Church that hath no Officers; one about the Covenant, and of what Covenant Baptiſme is the ſeale; one about the power of the Keyes; one about Ordination; one about Communion of Officers; one about maintenance of Officers, one about a private mans exerciſing his gifts; one about withdrawing from communion of ones own Church, Miniſtry and Ordinances; one about the externalls of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, whether they be contained determinately in the New Teſtament; one about the lawfulneſſe of tolerating another way then what is by Law eſtabliſhed; and yet it vvould have been unſeaſonable to have propounded ſome of theſe till the anſwers vve have given to them already in our Defence, have beene rendred invalid; and all theſe would not have amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to above 15. Queſtions, vvhat then vvould have become of your many ſcores. But your deſigne vvas under the forme of ſundry Queſtions, to aſſault us vvith ſundry Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, for very many of your Queſtions, yea the moſt of them are arguments which if we confute and overthrow (though your greateſt ſtrength be put forth in them, yet) you come off with honour, you aſſerted nothing poſitively but propounded only Queſtions; &amp; if we confute them not nor anſwer them clearly, we receive (as you imagine) a blot thereby; ſuch cunning there is in the vvay of your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. But vve rather chooſe to put you upon it to ſtate the Queſtion vvith us, and then to forme your Argument, and vve ſhall vvillingly ingage our ſelves then in anſwering of you; this is to ſet our ſelves upon equall ground vvith you; and you cannot, and we hope the Reader vvill not expect fairer proceedings from us. Notwithſtanding if you like not this, vvaite but a vvhile, till this preſent controverſie be iſſued betwixt us, and if others in the intrim doe not, we ſhall probably be at leaſure to undertake the particular anſwer of them in the forme they are preſented to us.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
